<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[devGiants]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/ddd.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2021-07-16T22:29:34+02:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Named constructor]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2020/03/04/named-constructors/"/>
            <updated>2020-03-04T17:30:00+01:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2020/03/04/named-constructors/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="how-to-create-an-instance-%3F">How to create an instance ?</h2>

<h3 id="classical-oop">Classical OOP</h3>

<p>In classical OOP approach, you will use the
<code>__construct</code> magic method to do the job. Let's reuse our <code>Ticket</code> entity 
described in <a href="https://devgiants.fr/blog/2020/03/02/symfony-workflow-component-walkthrough-part-1/">SymfonyWorkflow journey - part 1</a></p>

<pre><code class="php">/**
 * All attributes protected, stick to SOLID principles    
 */
class Ticket
{       
    protected $id;

    protected $title;

    /**
    * Classical constructor magic method
    */
    public function __construct()
    {

    }

}
</code></pre>

<p><em>Note : I cleared unnecessary stuff, such as getters/setters, annotations... 
So the rest look much more like a <strong>value object</strong>.</em></p>

<p>So far, so good. What's wrong with this? Nothing technically speaking, <strong>this does the job</strong>.
But what if the object is complex, and you have more than one way to create instance (from a business POV) ?
This is where <strong>named constructors</strong> come into light.</p>

<h3 id="named-constructor">Named constructor</h3>

<p>This is mostly a kind of static factory (a system to create an object) embedded in object class itself. Above example 
become :</p>

<p>```php
/**
  * All attributes protected, stick to SOLID principles<br />
  */
 class Ticket
 {<br />
     protected $id;</p>

<pre><code> protected $title;

 /**
 * Constructor becomes protected to ensure there is direct call
 */
 protected function __construct()
 {

 }

 /**
 * Named constructor example. Static to be called from class itself
 */
 public static function fromTitle(string $title): self
 {
    $ticket = new static();
    $ticket-&gt;setTitle($title);
    return $ticket;  
 } 
</code></pre>

<p>}
 ```</p>

<p>So instead of doing <code>$ticket = new Ticket()</code> you would do <code>$ticket = Ticket::fromTitle('new title')</code>.</p>

<p><em>Notes : 
- _Pay attention to <code>self</code> return type. This allow not to hardcode the class return type, hence offers 
dynamism on override (with precautions though).
- _In the same way, the <code>new static()</code> allow to instantiate current object instance. In case you extended <code>Ticket</code>,
you will obtain here the last-in-chain class type.</em></p>

<h2 id="advantages-and...-advantages">Advantages and... advantages</h2>

<p>Not really drawbacks here, let's focus on the advantages</p>

<h3 id="%C2%A0nice-semantics"> Nice semantics</h3>

<p><code>$ticket = Ticket::fromTitle('new title')</code> speaks for itself. More than creating an instance, you <strong>describe the
intent</strong> which is a key part in complex applications.</p>

<h3 id="override-constructors">Override constructors</h3>

<p>Unlike other languages (such as C++) , <strong>PHP can only have one constructor per class</strong>. If you stick to your class 
to get an instance, the only way to fulfill different instance creation scenarii is to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Low the signature exigence (parameters type-hinting, nullable,...)</li>
<li>Creates several checks and tests to ensure params passed on creation are still consistent</li>
</ul>

<p>As named constructors are simple static methods, and considering the fact that <code>__construct()</code> is no more available 
from outside world, you can create <strong>as much named constructors as you want</strong>. And guess what ?</p>

<ul>
<li>Design intents are still here (<code>Ticket::fromTitle()</code>, <code>Ticket::fromAnotherTicket()</code>...).</li>
<li>All coherence checks are separated and lies only in named constructor they belong to.</li>
</ul>

<p>Last but not least, this is totally <strong>framework agnostic</strong>. You can start using them now, with nothing but
intention.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>